Good morning.
早安。
Today we do China.
今天我们来聊中国。
Obviously we are in China and
显然我们在中国。
we know a lot of Chinese history, so
我们对中国历史了解很多，故此会快速而深入地讲述。
I will go fairly quickly and deeply.
这是一段快速而深入的讲述。
This is an opportunity for us to look
这是一次我们去观察的机会。
back on the theories we've developed over the course of this year
回顾我们在本年度课程中发展出的理论并真正思考它们在中国语境中的应用。
and really think about how they apply to the Chinese context.
这是一场机会，让我们检验我们的模型是否奏效。
It's a chance for us to see if our models work.
It's a chance for us tosee if our models work.
If they do work, then they would be true in the Western context
如果它们奏效，那么在西方语境中也成立
and also in the Chinese context.
同样在中国语境中也成立
It's also a chance for us to deeply interrogate our theories
这也是一次让我们深入检验理论的机会
and see where flaws might arise.
并观察可能出现的缺陷。
I'll be going through some Chinese history, but
我将回顾一些中国历史，但……
I will do so by applying the theories we've learned
我会通过运用我们学过的理论来完成。
so far. Mainly the Chinese history.
到目前为止，主要是中国历史。
Mainly the oceanic currents of history.
主要是历史的海洋潮流。
Alright, so let's get started.
好了，开始吧。
Today we're going to look at a question
今天我们要看一个对中国至关重要的问题
that is fundamental to China,
它是一个基本问题
which is, we know that
我们知道它是……
for the longest time China really was the
在最长的时间里，中国真正是世界上最优秀的文明。
civilization of poor excellence in the world.
它给我们带来了所有伟大的发明。
It gave us all the great inventions
that would make modernity possible, including the compass, paper, printmaking.
那将使现代化成为可能，包括指南针、纸张、印刷。
Gunpowder. But after the Song Dynasty,
火药。但在宋代之后，
which is about the year 1200,
约在1200年左右。
China stopped being creative.
中国停止了创造力。
And so why did this happen?
于是，为什么会出现这种情况？
And that is the question that
这就是问题所在。
will frame our discussion this morning.
今天的讨论将围绕此展开。
Alright, let's go over some quick Chinese history.
好了，我们快速回顾一下中国历史。
So, Chinese civilization,
于是，中国文明……
as you know, developed along the Yellow River.
正如你所知，黄河沿岸发展起来。
The Yellow River,
黄河，
it's perfect for agriculture.
它非常适合农业。
And as a result, population expanded very quickly.
于是，人口迅速增长。
When that happens, conflict and war will ensue.
随后便出现冲突与战争。
And that's what will give rise to settlements and fortified cities.
这便催生了聚落与城垣。
That will drive the development of the state and
那将推动国家的发展与
civilization and technology.
文明与技术的发展。
Okay? Um,
好的？嗯，
The hallmark of Chinese civilization is what we call,
中国文明的标志是我们所称的
the Warring States Period.
战国时期。
Uh, 春秋.
呃，春秋。
And at this time,
而在此时，
the foundations of Chinese civilization will come into being.
中国文明的基础将形成。
At this time, um,
此时，呃，
you will have something called the Hundred Schools of Thought.
你会有一个叫做百家思想的东西。
Um, Confucianism will develop,
呃，儒家会发展，
as will Taoism and Legalism.
道家和法家也会发展。
Okay? And these ideas will form the foundation of,
好的？这些思想将成为……的基础，
of, Chinese civilization.
……中国文明的基础。
And, as you can see, in this period,
而且，正如你所见，在此期间，
all these Hundred Schools of Thought developed because
所有这些百家思想的形成是因为
of a process we call, Open Cooperative Competition.
一个我们称之为开放协作竞争的过程。
Which, as we have discussed,
正如我们所讨论的那样。
is the main driver of innovation in human civilization.
是人类文明创新的主要驱动力。
Okay? Openness means that there is no centralized authority.
好？开放意味着没有集权机构。
Cooperation means that, even though there is no centralized authority,
合作意味着，即使没有集权机构，
the different states are trading,
不同的国家之间进行贸易，
communicating with each other, and they are intermarrying into each other.
彼此之间进行交流，并且相互通婚。
And competition means that
而竞争意味着
there is a lot of conflict between them.
有很多冲突在它们之间。
They are warring against each other for dominance in their region.
它们互相争夺各自地区的主导权。
Okay? And in this process,
好？在这个过程中，
this will give rise to the ideas,
这将催生思想，
the technology, the values, the culture, that
技术，价值观与文化，
will underpin Chinese civilization for the next 2,000 years.
这些将为中国文明在接下来两千年奠定基础。
Confucius is obviously, uh, who
孔子显然是这时代最被记住的人。
is best remembered from this era.
但你也有老子，他是道家的创始者。
But you also have Laozi, who is the founder of Taoism.
Okay? As well as Zhuangzi
好的？还有庄子
and Mozi.
和墨子。
Sunzi will, at this time, write his book, The Art of War.
孙子此时将写下《孙子兵法》。
So, in a process that is open cooperative competition,
于是，在开放协作竞争的过程中，
eventually, one state will emerge to conquer the rest.
最终会有一个国家崛起征服其余者。
And as we discussed,
正如我们所讨论的那样。
why the state emerges is because of three things.
为什么会出现这个国家是因为三件事。
Energy. They're much more energetic.
能量。他们更有活力。
They're much more ambitious. Second is openness.
他们更有雄心。第二是开放。
They're much more willing to adopt innovation.
他们更愿意采用创新。
They're much more willing to adopt innovation in the ruthless pursuit of military conquest.
他们更愿意在无情的军事征服追求中采用创新。
And they're opportunistic.
他们又很有机会主义。
Meaning that they will do whatever it takes to win.
意味着他们会不择手段取胜。
Okay? So, in this period, the state
好的？所以，在这段时间里，那个国家
that will eventually conquer all China and
最终将征服整个中国。
create the first empire is the Qing.
创建第一个帝国的是清朝。
And again, if you think about it,
再说一次，如果你思考它，
in the year 500 BCE,
在公元前500年，
we could not possibly predict that
我们根本就无法预料
the Qing would conquer and unite all of China.
清朝会征服并统一全中国。
Because of all these states,
在这些国家中，
the Qing was the poorest.
清朝是最贫穷的。
It was situated in the mountains,
它位于山中，
whereas the other states are situated in these fertile valleys.
而其他国家则位于这些肥沃的山谷中。
Its culture was not as developed as the rest.
它的文化发展不如其他国家。
And its population was smaller.
其人口也更少。
So, we couldn't predict that
于是我们就没能预料到。
the Qing would eventually unite all of China.
清朝最终会统一全中国。
But at the same time, in the year 500,
但同样在公元五百年，
we cannot have predicted that Rome would unite the Mediterranean.
我们也没能预料到罗马会统一地中海。
And we cannot have predicted that
我们也没能预料到
Macedonia would have united the Greek world.
马其达会统一希腊世界。
Alright? So,
好的？那么，
let's discuss very quickly why the Qing was able to succeed.
我们来快速讨论一下，为什么清朝能成功。
Okay. Even though this is the warring state,
好的。即便是战国时期，[107]
and there's a lot of warfare going on,
而且战事频繁，[108]
what we need to remember is that
我们需要记住的是
this warfare is heavily regulated.
这场战争被严格规制。
War, in this period, is almost like an aristocratic game.
战争，在此时期，几乎像一场贵族游戏。
Okay? So, there are stories where
好吧？于是，有些故事是这样的。
this general was laying siege to a city.
这位将军正在对城池进行围攻。
And the people inside were starving to death.
城内百姓已被饿得死去。
Which is what you do in a siege, right?
这就是你在围攻中所做的，对吧？
You starve the population to death.
你让人们饿死。
But the general felt tremendous regret
但将军却深感悔悟。
and guilt for putting the population under such misery.
并为把人们置于此苦难而感到愧疚。
So, he retreated and withdrew to give time for the population to recover.
于是他撤退，给人们恢复的时间。
And that was considered what was gentlemanly.
这被视为绅士之举。
Okay? That was what was considered chivalrous,
好的？那就是当时被视为骑士气概的事，文明的事。
civilized back then.
另一件事是……
Another story is that
Another story isthat
an army was crossing the river, which is a great time to attack them.
一支军队正渡河，正是进攻的好时机。
But the opposing army, let them cross the river,
但对方军队，让他们渡河，
because that is what is civilized.
因为这才是文明之举。
Okay? What is gentlemanly. So,
好的？那就是骑士气概的事。
this period was heavily regulated
这段时间被骑士的行为准则严格规范。
by a gentleman's code of conduct.
by a gentleman'scode of conduct.
Okay? And then you ask yourself, why is that the case?
好的？然后你会问自己，为什么会是这样？
And the answer is that, remember,
答案是，记住，
this is an open cooperative competition environment,
这是一个开放的合作竞争环境。
in which, even though these states are at war,
在这种情况下，即使这些国家处于战争状态，仍然有大量的联姻。
there's still a lot of intermarriage between them.
仍有大量的贸易和交流。
There's still a lot of trade, a lot of communication.
仍有大量的贸易和沟通。
So, these states are not trying to use warfare to overturn the social order,
于是，这些国家并不是用战争来颠覆社会秩序，
because they benefit from the status quo.
因为它们从现状中获益。
They're using warfare as a means to maintain the social order.
它们把战争当作维持社会秩序的手段。
And that's why warfare is extremely heavily regulated.
于是，战争被极其严格地规范化。
Okay? And so,
好的？于是，……
let's think about the Peloponnesian War between Athens and Sparta.
让我们来思考雅典与斯巴达之间的伯罗奔尼亚战争。
When we looked at the war, we know that
当我们回顾战争时，知道……
the Peloponnesian War was extremely bloody.
伯罗奔尼亚战争非常血腥。
It was extremely deadly. But at the same time, it was extremely regulated.
它既致命又被严格规范。
And a lot of their strategies didn't really make any sense.
并且他们的许多策略确实毫无意义。
It was really about defeating the enemy.
其实就是要击败敌人。
So, for example, we know that in Sparta,
于是，例如我们知道在斯巴达，
there are people called the helots, who are basically slaves to the Spartan people.
有一种人叫赫洛特，基本上是斯巴达人的奴隶。
And the helots outnumber the Spartans ten to one.
赫洛特的人口数是斯巴达人的十倍。
So, all Athens had to do was to take the Helots and say,
于是，雅典只需把赫洛特抓住，然后说，
if you fight for us, if you revolt against your masters,
如果你为我们而战，如果你反叛你的主人，我们将赐予你自由。
we will grant you freedom.
这就是雅典所需做的事。可雅典却未曾做到。
That's all Athens had to do. But Athens never did that.
Because by doing that,
因为这样做，你会打乱雅典所获益的社会秩序，并掀起一场革命。
you would disrupt the social order from
which Athens benefited, and you would unleash a revolution that
因为这样做，你会打乱雅典所获益的社会秩序，并掀起一场革命。
could possibly engulf the entire Greek world.
可能会席卷整个希腊世界。
Also, even though Sparta and Athens were enemies,
此外，尽管斯巴达与雅典是敌人，
they were united by intermarriage
他们通过联姻而团结在一起。
among their elites.
在他们的精英中。
They had a similar culture.
他们有相似的文化。
And they historically were allies,
而他们历史上是盟友。
especially against the Persians.
尤其针对波斯人。
So, warfare at this time was about maintaining the status quo,
于是，那个时代的战争主要是维护现状，
rather than overturning the status quo.
而非推翻现状。
And this presents an opportunity
于是出现了机会
for the Qing Dynasty,
给清朝带来机会
which is in the margins of the status quo.
位于现状边缘
So, the Qing Dynasty started to invent warfare in a way
于是，清朝开始以一种方式发明战争
that opportunistically took advantage of the status quo situation.
并且以机会主义的方式利用现状局面
And they committed themselves to total warfare,
并且他们将自己投入到全方战争中
meaning their entire society
其整个社会的结构被设计成能让他们战胜敌人。
was engineered in a way to allow them to win against their enemies.
于是，清朝在此时具有的某些特征。
So, certain characteristics about the Qing Dynasty at this time,
first is the idea of legalism.
第一点是法家思想。
Draconian laws that
多利安式的法律，
force a population to behave in a certain way.
迫使人们按一定方式行事。
Something that
某件事
is very fundamental to the idea of legalism is collective responsibility.
很基本的法家思想是集体责任。
What that means is that if you commit a crime,
这意味着如果你犯了罪行，
you'll be punished, but so will your entire family.
你会被惩罚，连你全家也会受罚。
The idea of collective responsibility is pioneered at
集体责任的概念在此时被开创。
this time in order to maintain a very strict society
为维持极严社会，集体责任被引入。
that can be purposed for war.
可以用于战争的目的。
So, that's the first thing. Second, legalism.
首先是这个，第二个是法家。
Second thing is the idea of centralization, meaning
第二个是中央集中的概念，意味着
that you have a bureaucracy,
你有官僚制，
you have centralization, and
你有中央集成，
this allows you to actually expand very quickly.
这让你能迅速扩张。
It allows you to expand and govern new territories
它让你能够扩张并统治新领土
that you conquer.
你所征服的
And the third, of course, is total war,
第三点，当然是全军战
meaning you devote all your resources to
意味着你把所有资源投入到
warfare in order to conquer your enemies.
用战争来征服敌人。
The Qing Dynasty was also known for its openness.
清朝也以开放著称。
So, if you were a man of talent and you could contribute to the military
所以，如果你是有才干的人，并能为军队作贡献
and the bureaucracy, they would welcome you.
而官僚也会接待你。
So, think of the Qing as a revolutionary system
所以，把清朝视为一个革命性制度
that sought to overturn the status quo.
那种旨在推翻现状的
And the other states like Wei,
以及其他诸如魏的诸侯国
Zhao, Han, and Chu, especially Chu, they were trying to maintain a status quo.
赵、韩、楚，尤其是楚，正试图维持现状。
And therefore, they were not that
于是，他们并非如此
well equipped to deal with the challenge from the Qing.
已充分装备，准备迎接清朝的挑战。
Now, we know that the Qing would unite all of China,
现在，我们知道清朝会统一整个中国，
but because their system was
但因为他们的制度是
so draconian,
如此严厉
eventually the other states would rebel against them.
最终其他诸侯国会起义反对他们
And this would eventually lead to
于是，这最终会导致汉朝。
the Han Dynasty.
汉朝。
Now, the Han Dynasty is actually,
现在，汉朝实际上是，
well, even though the Han Dynasty
好吧，虽然汉朝是
disparages the Qing, right?
我们对清朝的评价是这样吗？
So, our very conception of the Qing comes from Han historians
因此，我们对清朝的基本认识来自汉代史学家
who tell us that the Qing buried scholars
谁告诉我们清朝埋人文士
and they burned books.
并且焚书
And that, in our eyes, is barbaric, right?
在我们眼里，这就是野蛮，对吧？
We don't know that's true.
我们不确定这是真的。
We know that the Qing practiced heavy censorship.
我们知道清朝实行了严厉的审查。
So, those hundred schools of thought, a lot of these books were censored
于是，那些百家学派，许多书籍被审查
and destroyed during this period.
并在此期间被毁灭。
But we don't know for a fact that they buried scholars, okay?
但我们不确定他们确实埋人文士，行吗？
But this is what... So, the Han Dynasty is trying to disparage,
但这就是……所以，汉朝正在尝试贬低，
trying to refute the Qing Dynasty.
再试以驳清朝。
That said, the Han Dynasty continues
那样说，汉朝继续
the system first introduced
系统最初的引入
by the Qing, okay?
由清朝完成，行吗？
The Han is really, at this point,
汉朝此时真的，
the height of Chinese civilization.
中国文明的巅峰。
There's a confluence, there's an arrogance to the Han.
有汇聚，也有汉朝的自负。
And one of the top priorities for the Han is, now that they've united China,
而且，汉朝的首要任务之一是，既然已统一中国，
they have to deal with the Northern steppe people, okay?
他们必须应对北方的草原民族，行吗？
Remember that throughout history,
记住，历史上，草原民族一直是文明最艰难的挑战。
the steppe people have proven to be the most daunting challenge for civilizations.
他们是极其……
They are extremely...
他们非常……
They're ferocious warriors.
他们是凶猛的战士。
And the steppe people will eventually give rise to the Mongols.
草原民族最终会孕育成蒙古人。
At this point, the main adversary
此时，汉族的主要对手被称为匮奴人。
of the Han are called the Xiongnu people. And
汉朝对匮奴的政策是消灭。
the Han Dynasty is committed to a policy of eradication against the Xiongnu,
okay?
好的？
And this policy of eradication will force the Xiongnu to migrate westwards.
而这项消灭政策会迫使匮奴向西迁徙。
And eventually, they will...
最终，他们会……
These people will start to even threaten Rome itself.
这些人甚至会威胁罗马本身。
Until the Han... The Han people are descendants of the Xiongnu,
直到汉... 汉人是匮奴的后裔，
okay? But over time,
好了？但随着时间的推移，
because of this conflict between the Han
因为汉与北方草原民族的冲突，
and the Northern steppe people,
这将给汉国造成巨大压力。
this will create tremendous strain on the Han.
And eventually, the policy will evolve to one of cooperation
最终，这一政策将演变为合作型
and dependency.
以及依赖。
And so what will happen is there will be a lot of trade,
于是会出现大量贸易，
there will be a lot of intermarriage,
将会有大量的通婚
and the steppe people will be hired as mercenaries.
并且草原人将被雇佣为雇佣兵。
For internal conflicts within China, okay?
至于中国内部冲突，行吗？
So, open cooperation,
于是，展开合作，
competition, now switches from the Han, which
竞争，现在从汉转向…
has become a centralized power, to the steppe people.
已成为一个集中的力量，对草原人来说。
So within these people, and there's quite a lot of different tribes,
于是，在这些人中，且有相当多的不同部落
there will be now tremendous competition.
现在将出现巨大的竞争。
And one group, one tribe, that will eventually triumph
有一支部落，最终会胜出的，叫做顺北，行吗？
is called the Shunbei, okay?
And the Shunbei will give rise to which dynasty? Do you guys know?
那么顺北会孕育哪一朝？你们知道吗？
Okay, but Shunbei will give rise to which major Chinese dynasty?
好的，但顺北会孕育哪一大朝？
You guys should know this. What comes after the Han?
你们应该知道这点。汉朝之后是什么？
The Tang Dynasty, okay?
唐朝，行吗？
So this is one thing that is misunderstood.
所以这点是被误解的。
The Han Dynasty is really the last Chinese dynasty.
汉朝才是最后一个中国朝代。
It is the last ethnic leader of the Chinese dynasty,
它是中国朝代的最后一位民族领袖
committed to the protection and propagation of Chinese culture.
致力于保护与传播中国文化。
The Tang Dynasty, the founders,
唐朝，创始者，
the Li family, they're actually of the Shunbei tribe, okay?
李氏家族，实际上是顺北族，行吗？
And as a result, they will switch from a,
于是他们会从……转变为……
they will switch China into a universal, multicultural empire, okay?
他们会把中国变成一个普世、多元文化的帝国，行吗？
The Tang Dynasty is famous for being extremely open, tolerant,
唐朝以极度开放、包容著称，
and inclusive, okay?
并且包容，行吗？
All right, so this is the Tang Dynasty, which
好的，唐朝就是这样，且是……
is considered the height of power,
它被认为是力量的巅峰
the height of Chinese power in the world.
中国在世界上的巅峰
The Tang Dynasty will try to expand westwards into Central Asia,
唐朝将向西部扩展至中亚
and it will start the Silk Road and
并将开启丝绸之路
trade networks all around the world.
贸易网络遍布全球。
Buddhism, at this point, will come into China, and
佛教此时传入中国，且会在某些时期成为国教。
it will become, at certain points, a state religion.
它将成为某些时期的国教。
Okay? But
好的？但
there are many problems with the Tang Dynasty.
唐朝有许多问题
So there's a heavy reliance on generals to fight wars,
于是大依赖将领打仗
and this will eventually lead to the An Lushan Rebellion, okay?
于是最终导致安禄山之乱，好吗？
Which lasts for almost 10 years.
安禄山之乱持续近十年。
An Lushan is the top general of the Tang Dynasty,
安禄山是唐朝的顶尖将领。
and because he's given too much power,
并且他被赋予过多权力，
he has too much independence, he's much too trusted by the emperor,
他拥有过多独立，皇帝对他也过多信任，
he eventually rebels and seeks the throne for himself.
他最终起兵自立皇位。
Okay? This rebellion will kill
好的？这场叛乱将导致…
anywhere between a third to half of the Tang population.
在唐朝人口的三分之一到二分之一之间死亡…
Okay? 60 million to 30 million people.
大约六千万人到三千万人。”
And this is devastating and
而这又是毁灭性的，且…
traumatic for the Tang Dynasty, okay?
对唐朝来说又是创伤性的，好吗？
But somehow it recovers.
但它又奇迹般恢复了。
But then, but then
但随后，随后…
you will have another rebellion called the Huang Chao Rebellion,
你将会有一次叫黄巢之乱的叛乱，
which will end the Tang Dynasty. I'll talk about the Huang Chao later on.
它将结束唐朝。稍后我会再谈黄巢。
The Tang Dynasty will give rise to the Song Dynasty,
唐朝将孕育宋朝的崛起
and the Song Dynasty will adopt a
宋朝将采纳一项外交政策
policy of diplomacy to
……
build assimilation with the northern tribes.
建造与北方部落的同化。
Okay? They're trying to avoid the trap of the Tang,
好的？他们正试图避免唐朝的陷阔，
where you give too much power to a general, and the general will rebel.
给将领过多权力，结果将领起兵反叛。
Okay? So a lot of power in the Song Dynasty, at the time of the Song Dynasty,
好的？宋朝时期，宋朝拥有大量权力，
a lot of power will be invested in the imperial bureaucracy.
大量权力将投入到朝廷官僚中。
Okay? That's the Song. Eventually,
好的？这就是宋朝。最终，
the Song Empire will be carved up and conquered.
宋朝将被分割并被征服。
Eventually, the ultimate winners of this war will be the Mongols,
最终，这场战争的最终胜者将是蒙古人，
who in the year 1279
他们在1279年
conquers the entirety of the Song Empire, and unites China.
征服宋朝全境，统一中国。
Okay? But the Yuan,
好的吗？但元朝，
the Mongols are considered a foreign dynasty.
蒙古被视为外来王朝。
So I mentioned that
于是我提到，唐朝其实是非汉族的。
the Tang Dynasty is actually non -Chinese.
但蒙古人是……。
But the Mongols
understood themselves to be non -Chinese, and
他们自认为是非汉族的，且
as a result, they discriminated against Chinese people,
于是他们对汉人产生了歧视，且
which ultimately led to rebellion that
最终导致了起义
will establish the Ming Empire,
将建立明朝
and eventually the Ming Empire will give way to the Qing Empire.
最终明朝又让位给清朝
The Manchus are just another iteration of the Mongol people.
满族只是又一次蒙古人的迭代
They will rule China until 1911,
他们统治中国直到1911年，帝国被推翻，建立了共和国，随后自然出现了中华人民共和国。
when the empire is overthrown, a republic is established,
and this gives way to, of course, the People's Republic of China.
他们统治中国直到1911年，帝国被推翻，建立了共和国，随后自然出现了中华人民共和国。
Okay? So the big question, again,
好的？那么大问题再次出现，
what we're looking at is, why is it that the Song Dynasty
我们要看的是什么，为什么宋朝是最后一个有创造力的朝代？
is the last creative dynasty?
All right? And
好了？然后
if we use the idea of open cooperative competition,
如果我们用开放协作竞争的概念，
then we know the answer.
我们就能知道答案。
All right? And the answer is this.
好了？答案就是这样。
Previous dynasties were not able to exert national control.
前朝未能形成国家统治。
They were always competing against
它们总是相互竞争。
other states within China proper.
其他国家在中国本土内。
Okay? So you look at the Han Dynasty.
好了？所以你看汉朝。
Well, the Han Dynasty would give way to dozens of other states,
嗯，汉朝会让出几十个其他国家。
that would compete against each other.
它们相互竞争。
Okay? So in theory, the Qing
好了？所以在理论上，清朝……
and the Han united China, but not for long.
……与汉朝合并中国，但不久。
All right? And
好的？然后
the same is true for the Tang as well.
同样的情况也适用于唐朝。
China, for the longest time, was just too large,
中国在最长的时间里，刚好太大。
too diverse, to be unified centrally.
多样化，需中央统一。
And as a result,
于是，
the idea of open cooperative competition would still give rise to a lot of innovation.
开放合作竞争的理念仍将催生大量创新。
But starting at the time of the Song, we see a radical change.
但从宋朝开始，我们看到一次根本的变化。
Look at the Song, okay?
看宋朝，行吗？
The Song is pretty united.
宋朝相当统一。
And the Yuan is extremely united.
并且元朝极为统一。
So the Yuan Dynasty is able to unite all of China.
于是，元朝能够统一全中国。
And then after the Yuan Dynasty, the Ming is also pretty united,
随后，明朝也相当统一。
and the Qing is extremely united.
并且清朝极为统一。
Okay? So in other words, the answer is this.
好？换句话说，答案就是这样。
After the Song, and starting with the Yuan,
宋朝之后，从元朝开始，
China became nationally unified.
中国实现了全国统一。
And it was able,
并且它得以，
the center was able to exert control of the provinces in a way
中央得以控制各省。
that was not true before in Chinese history.
那在中国历史上并非如此。
Okay? So the idea of open competitive competition died with the Song Dynasty.
好？所以开放竞争的概念在宋朝已消亡。
And that's why after the Song,
这也是宋朝之后的原因。
China stopped being creative.
中国停止了创造力。
Okay? So that's the answer.
好？这就是答案。
But then this gives rise to another question,
但随后又提出了另一个问题。
which is, how was China able
哪样呢？中国是怎样实现民族统一的？
to create national unity?
好的？好的。
All right? All right.
So to answer this question,
于是为回答这个问题，
I want to refer to the
我想引用
work of Professor Wang Yuhua.
王玉华教授的研究。
He is a professor of Chinese history at Harvard.
他是哈佛大学的中国史教授。
Okay? And he wrote a new book called The Rise and Fall of Imperialism.
好的？他写了一本新书，叫《帝国的兴衰》。”
The Rise and Fall of Imperial China. And it's a wonderful book.
《帝国的兴衰》是关于中国帝国的书，真是一本精彩的著作。
If you're interested in Chinese history, I strongly recommend that you look at this book.
如果你对中国历史感兴趣，我强烈推荐你去看看这本书。
All right. So
好的。那么
he begins the book by asking a central question.
他在书的开头提出了一个核心问题。
And the central question is this.
并且核心问题是这个。
We know that the Tang Dynasty was really the height of Chinese power.
我们知道唐朝确实是中国力量的巅峰。
It had about a quarter of the world's GDP.
它约占全球GDP的四分之一。
And it influenced the cultures of Korea, Japan.
并且影响了韩国和日本的文化。
And it was an extremely diverse,
并且它是一个极其多样的，
inclusive, multicultural empire that
并且是一个包容的、多元文化的帝国。
introduced Buddhism to China.
引入佛教到中国。
Okay? But
好的？但是
the problem with the Tang is their emperors didn't really live
唐朝的问题在于他们的皇帝并不真正在位。
that long. Five emperors, at least five emperors,
那段很长。至少有五位皇帝，至少五位皇帝，
during the Tang Dynasty were deposed by the elite.
唐朝期间，皇帝被贵族推翻。
The aristocracy got together and were through the emperor, usually by killing him.
贵族聚集起来，通常通过杀皇帝来更换皇帝。
Okay? So this is the Tang Dynasty.
好的吗？这就是唐朝。
But when you look at the Qing,
但若你看清清朝，
Qing only had 5% of the world's GDP.
清朝的国内生产总值仅占全球的5%。
And it was wracked by internal rebellions like the Taiping Rebellion.
并且被内部叛乱如太平起义所撕裂。
And it was far behind in terms of science,
并且在科学技术方面远落后于欧洲。
technology to Europe.
But the emperors, like Tianlong,
但皇帝们，如天龙，他们能统治六十年安稳。
they could rule for 60 years peacefully.
好？他们顺利登基。
Okay? They transitioned into a throne peacefully.
Okay? They transitionedinto a throne peacefully.
And they died peacefully. So the Qing, even
并且他们安然去世。于是清朝，即便…
though it marked a low point in Chinese prosperity,
虽然这标志着中国繁荣的低谷…
the emperors lived for a long time,
皇帝们却长寿…
which meant that the bureaucracy,
这意味着官僚，中心，真的很稳定。
the center, was really stable.
这就是一个悖论。
This is a paradox. Okay?
好的？
Why is it that when China is wealthy, the emperor is weak,
为什么中国富裕时皇帝弱，但皇帝强时中国贫穷？
but when the emperor is strong, China is poor?
这就是一个悖论。
That's a paradox that
That's a paradoxthat
Professor Wang Yuhua is trying to answer in his book.
王玉华教授正在他的书中尝试回答。
Okay. So he, so, I mean, he is,
好的。所以他，我是说，他是，
he used a lot of social science
他用了大量社会科学。
analysis and research for his book.
分析与研究为他的书做准备。
So first of all, what he does is he analyzes the probability as an emperor
首先，他所做的是把概率当作皇帝来分析。
that you are deposed by the elite.
你被精英推翻的那一刻。
Okay? And it turns out, like,
好的？结果是，像这样，
the tongue was really the height.
舌头真是高点。
But then when you get to the song,
但随后当你进入歌曲时，
the probability decreases significantly.
概率显著下降。
Okay? But
好吧？但
at the same time, what we need to understand is,
与此同时，我们需要理解的是，
even though the emperor lived longer,
即使皇帝寿命更长，
the state's ability to collect taxes,
国家的税收能力，
to control the economy, decreased over time.
经济掌控力随时间而减弱。
Okay? So you can see that starting the year zero,
好的？所以你可以看到，从零年开始，一路向下的斜率。
all the way down, there's a downward slope.
现在，这条线并不是直线向下。
Now, this is not straight down.
Now, this is notstraight down.
Okay? There are peaks.
好的？有高峰。
Right? So you go down, then you go up, you go down.
对吧？先往下，再往上，接着往下。
The up is when a new dynasty starts.
上升是新朝代开始时。
And so at this time, the new dynasty is run by a very strong leader.
于是此时，新朝由一位非常强大的领袖执掌。
Like, for example, Zhu Yuanzhang of the Ming Dynasty,
比如说，明朝的朱元璋，明朝的创始者。
the founder of the Ming Dynasty. Okay?
好吧？
These are extremely capable leaders,
这些是极为能干的领袖，
and they are supported by really talented bureaucrats.
他们得到了才华横溢的官僚相助，
And at this point, they're able to collect a lot of taxes,
此时他们已能收集大量税赋。
which strengthens the center.
加强了中央。
But over time, the trend is fairly clear.
但随着时间推移，趋势相当明显。
Starting at the time of the Song,
从宋代开始。
you see a steep decline in
你会看到……的急剧下降
the state's ability to collect taxes.
国家的税收能力。
Okay? The only exceptions are around the year 1600,
好的？唯一的例外是大约1600年左右。
when the Ming transitions to the Qing.
当明朝过渡到清朝时。
Okay? And
好的？
so what Professor Wang Yi Hua has discovered is,
于是王一华教授发现的就是，
the reason why you have this transition
这就是你看到的过渡原因。
is the emperor,
是皇帝，
starting around the time of the Song, he's actually figured out a way
从宋代开始，他实际上找到了一个办法
to divide and conquer the elite.
分而治之，统御精英。
Okay? So the elite, when they are united,
好的吗？于是精英们统一时，
they're able to promote strong centralized policies
他们能够推动强有序的政策，促进国家增长。
that promote national growth.
But
但
the centralized elite can always threaten the emperor,
集中的精英可以随时威胁皇帝，
who is dependent on the
谁依赖于
elite for
精英为
their support in
他们在...的支持
the military and in government.
军队与政府。
Okay? Starting around the Song,
好了？从宋朝开始，
the centralized elite is now broken down into localized elite.
中央精英现在被拆分成地方精英。
So the trick that
于是，掌握强大中心的诀窍是
China has discovered in maintaining
中国在保持强大中心时发现的
a strong center is by localizing the elites.
通过把精英本土化
Okay? So the idea is, you localize the elites.
好的？所以思路是，把精英本土化。
When you localize the elites, you can implement a policy we call divide
当你把精英本土化时，你可以实行我们称之为“分而治之”的政策。
and conquer.
Okay? So you get the elites in this province to fight amongst themselves.
好的？所以你让这省的精英互相争斗。
If they're too busy fighting amongst themselves,
如果他们忙于互相争斗，
they're not going to ever rebel against you, and
他们就不会再起义。
they're not going to build alliances with other provinces to ever challenge you.
他们不会与其他省份结盟来挑战你。
Okay? And their priorities and
好吧？他们的优先级和焦点在省份上。
focus is in the provinces,
focus is in theprovinces,
and they really don't care what you guys do in the capital.
他们真的不在乎你们在首都做什么。
All right? So that's the thesis.
好的？这就是论点。
All right. And what Professor Wang Yihua says is,
好的。王一华教授说的是，
the main mechanism that
主要机制是科举。
the emperor used in order to achieve this radical cultural shift is the kezhu.
皇帝用科举来实现这场文化大转变。
Okay? The kezhu is a civil service examination
好？科举就是科举考试。
that promoted bureaucrats into positions of power.
促使官员升入权力职位。
Okay? The kezhu, the civil service examination.
好？科举，科举考试。
And so the history of the kezhu is
于是科举的历史是。
that it was introduced briefly in the Sui, and then the Tang Dynasty
那是先在隋朝短暂引入，随后唐朝开始使用。
started to use it.
好？但真正是宋朝。
Okay? But it was really the Song Dynasty
that really systemized and promoted it.
那才真正把它制度化并推广。
Okay? Basically, the Song Dynasty
好？基本上，宋朝
institutionalized the kezhu.
宋朝把科举制度化。
Okay? And before the kezhu, it was really an aristocratic system
好的？在科举之前，它确实是一个贵族制度，你必须是贵族出生才能成为高级官员。
where you had to be of noble birth in order to become a high official
in government, which is true for most cultures.
好的？在科举之前，它确实是一个贵族制度，你必须是贵族出生才能成为高级官员。
Okay? So that's what he argues.
好？这就是他所说的。
All right. So
好的。那么
he looks at times of major rebellions.
他看的是大起义的时代。
And what he shows is that
而他所展示的是
whenever there's massive climate change,
每当出现大规模气候变化时，
you have violence.
你就会出现暴力。
And when you have a centralized system,
当你拥有一个集中的制度时，
what often happens is that the nobility engage in rent -seeking behavior.
通常会出现贵族们寻租的行为。
Basically, they exploit the peasants.
基本上，他们会剥削农民。
And that's fine if the weather is good.
如果天气好就没问题。
But when the weather is bad and the peasants don't have enough to eat,
但天气差，农民吃不饱时，往往会起义。
they often rebel.
他们常常会起义。
Okay? And in the Tang, this would culminate in something called the Huang Chao Rebellion,
好的？在唐朝，这最终演变成了黄巢起义，[503]
which would last for 10 years when
它持续了十年，[504]
a salt merchant in Huang Chao sorry,
一个盐商黄巢，[505]
a salt merchant named Huang Chao,
一个名叫黄巢的盐商
he would lead an uprising that would overwhelm and destroy
他将发动起义，席卷并摧毁唐朝。
the Tang Dynasty.
The thing that's important for us to remember is
我们要记住的重点是
that he would go all the way to Chang 'an.
他会一路去长安。
And Chang 'an is where all the elite live.
长安是所有精英聚居的地方。
Okay? There are about 200 aristocratic families in the Tang Dynasty.
好的？唐朝大约有200个贵族家族。
And they were all killed in this rebellion.
他们在这场起义中全部被消灭。
When you remove the aristocracy,
去掉贵族后，
this gives the Song Dynasty room to implement a new policy
这让宋朝有机会实施新政策，并确保贵族再次不复兴。
and ensure that an nobility cannot arise again.
好的？所以这就是黄巢起义的意义。
Okay? So that is the significance of the Huang Chao Rebellion.
It eliminated the idea of aristocracy in China.
它消除了中国贵族的概念。
Okay. So,
好的。于是，
Professor Wang Yu Hua, he looks,
王玉华教授，看起来，
what he does is he shows
他所做的就是展示
you how networks work in China.
你如何在中国看到网络的运作方式。
So during the Tang Dynasty, as you can see,
因此，在唐朝期间，正如你所见。
there are centers
有中心
which then moved to the provinces.
随后迁移到各省
Okay? So these families are all interconnected together.
这些家族相互连通
Because there's only 200 aristocratic families.
因为只有200个贵族家族。
If you are a wealthy family in a province,
如果你是某省的富裕家族，
what you want to do is intermarry into one of these aristocratic families.
你想做的就是与其中一个贵族家族联姻。
Okay? Because that's the best way to ensure your advantage
好的？因为这是确保你优势的最佳方式。
and privilege in life.
和生活中的特权。
Okay? So this is during the Tang Dynasty
好的？这就是唐朝时期。
when families are united.
当家族联合时。
Nationally.
全国性。
But when you get to the Song Dynasty,
但当你到达宋朝时，
what you will see is that the center has been localized.
你会看到的是，中心已被本土化。
Meaning it's been spread out.
意思是已经分散开来。
And what you will also see is that these networks are localized.
你还会看到这些网络已经本土化。
They're not connected together now nationally.
它们现在在全国范围内已不再相连。
Alright? And
好的？
this again allows now the emperor to divide and conquer.
这再次让皇帝能够分而治之。
Alright? So let's just do a comparison.
好吧？那我们来做个比较。
The tongue and the Song.
舌与宋。
As you can see, what's really important is, look at this guys,
如你所见，真正重要的是，看看这些人。
the networks become more and more localized over time.
网络随时间逐渐本土化。
It is the deliberate policy of the imperial bureaucracy
这是皇室官僚的有意政策。
to localize elite networks.
把精英网络本土化。
So that they can never unite and challenge the center.
于是它们才能永不统一，挑战中央。
Okay? So these networks are becoming much more fractured
好吧？于是这些网络随时间变得更碎片化、局部化。
and localized over time.
Alright? Okay.
好的？好吧。
So the main benefit of this system is of course national unity.
所以这个制度的主要好处当然是国家统一。
So again, during the Han,
再说一次，汉朝时期……
you have all these different provinces
你拥有所有这些不同的省份
that form their own dynasties and which challenge the center.
它们形成自己的朝代并挑战中央
So China was in a constant process of war.
于是中国处于不断的战争之中
The Tang Dynasty was a bit better.
唐朝稍好一点。
But when you get to the Song, the Yuan,
但到了宋、元、明、清，整体上都相当统一。
the Ming, and the Qing, it's all pretty unified nationally.
the Ming, and the Qing, it'sall pretty unified nationally.
Okay? By localizing elites,
好的？通过本土化精英，你确保中央可被挑战。
you ensure the center can be challenged.
并且因此，
And as a result,
you give a semblance of national unity.
你给人以国家统一的表象。
But the problem with this, as we know,
但正如我们所知，这其中的问题是……
is it comes at the cost of innovation.
它的代价是创新的牺。
Which will make China insular,
这将使中国在长期内变得内陆化、贫困且分裂。
poor, and divided in the long term.
而且这并不是一个真正可持续的制度。
And it's not really a sustainable system.
And it's not reallya sustainable system.
But that's a system that China has chosen to adopt for the past thousand years.
但这正是中国过去千年所选择的制度。
A divide and conquer policy against the local elites.
对地方豪族的分而治之策。
Alright. So
好的，明白了。
let's look at another example of how China became insular,
让我们再看一个例子，说明中国如何变得内陆化、贫困且分裂。
poor, and divided over time. So
于是，这是一张地图。
this is a map of the
this is a map ofthe
top 30 cities by population throughout Chinese history.
全史上人口最多的前30座城市
As you can see, during the Western Han, during the Han Dynasty,
正如你所见，西汉时期，汉朝期间，
most of these cities are centered
这些城市大多集中在
around the Huang He, the Yellow River.
在黄河周边，黄河。
Okay? That makes sense because that's where Chinese civilization began.
对吧？这很合理，因为那是中国文明的起点。
But starting from the Tang,
但从唐代开始，
they're starting to spread out more.
它们开始向外扩散。
And by the time of the Song,
到宋代时，它们已聚集到海岸。
they're actually congregating to the coast.
Right? So why is this happening?
对吧？那是为什么发生的原因吗？
It's happening because of maritime trade
它发生是因为阿拔斯王朝发起的海上贸易
initiated by the Abbasid Caliphate.
由阿拔斯王朝发起的海上贸易
Remember in our last class, we learned about the Islamic Golden Age
记得上节课我们学过伊斯兰黄金时代
and how the Abbasid Caliphate became
以及阿拔斯王朝如何变得如此富有
so wealthy that it established trade networks all around the world.
并建立起遍布全球的贸易网络
And these trade networks were so powerful that
而这些贸易网络如此强大，以至于
they could influence the national economic development of China.
它们可以影响中国的国民经济发展。
Okay? And we can expect
好的？我们可以预期。
that because of maritime trade, over time,
因为海上贸易，随着时间推移，所有大城都迁至海岸。
all the major cities of China would all shift to the coast.
于是，所有大城都迁至海岸。
And that's why
于是，正是因为如此
when Zhu Yuanzhang came into power,
当朱元璋登上权位时
he initiated a policy of closed borders.
他实行了闭关政策。
He shut down maritime trade.
他关闭了海上贸易。
Because he was afraid
因为他害怕
that if this continued, then
如果这样继续下去，
all the power would be located in the coastal areas
所有的力量都集中在沿海地区
and therefore the north, the west,
于是北方、西方
the south will become much poorer and therefore they are much more incentivized to trade.
南方将变得更贫穷，因此更有动力去贸易。
the Chinese were able to rebel. Also, the coastal areas
中国人能够起义。还有，沿海地区
would have so much power that they could ultimately depose him.
会拥有如此强大的力量，最终能推翻他。
Okay? And that's why Zhu Yuanzhang would impose a policy of maritime trade ban.
好了？这就是朱元璋实行海上贸易禁令的原因。
And this would make China much more insular and weak
这将使中国更为内向，变得更弱。
and poor. Okay?
又贫穷。好了？
So again, remember back to the Islamic Golden Age,
于是再次，回想起伊斯兰黄金时代，
when the Islamic world united all the entire world and tried to pull China into its system.
那时伊斯兰世界统一了全世界，并试图把中国拉入其体系。
But because of that, it was causing
但由于此，导致
wealth inequality in China.
中国的财富不平等
And that's why the Ming Dynasty will shut down this trade network.
这就是明朝将关闭此贸易网络的原因。
Not completely, but mostly.
不完全，但大多是。
Okay? And that's why you see this massive Chinese immigration
好了？这就是你看到大规模中国移民的原因。
to Southeast Asia.
到东南亚。
Because they want to maintain these trade networks.
因为他们想维持这些贸易网络。
And there's a trade ban
还有一项贸易禁令在明朝实施。
enforced in the Ming Dynasty.
enforced in theMing Dynasty.
And the Qing Dynasty will continue this policy as well.
并且清朝也会继续这一政策。
For China,
对中国而言，
the priority is internal stability
优先是内部稳定
rather than wealth and prosperity.
而非财富与繁荣
All right. So, that's a quick introduction.
好的。那是一个快速介绍。
All right. Any questions about this so far?
好的。到目前为止还有什么问题吗？
Are you guys clear? Okay.
你们明白了吗？好的。
Any questions?
还有问题吗？
You guys are clear, right? Okay.
你们明白了吧？好的。
All right. So, that is Professor Wang Yihua's argument.
好的。那就是王一华教授的论点。
And as you can see,
而且你可以看到，
it's it's a very he backs up with a lot of data.
它确实用大量数据来支撑。
Okay? I'm just presenting to you his argument.
好的，我只是在向你们展示他的论点。
Okay. So, now, I want to talk more about
好的。接下来，我想再多聊聊
the idea of
关于这个想法
the imperial bureaucracy. Because
帝国官僚制。因为
this will inform and help us better understand world history as we move along.
这将帮助我们更好地理解世界历史的进程。
Okay? So, to better understand the rise of imperial bureaucracy,
好的？所以，为了更好地理解帝国官僚制的崛起。
let's let's first re -examine the world history the history of Rome.
先让我们重新审视罗马的世界史。
Okay? So, in the year 500
好的？于是，在公元前五百年。
BCE, okay,
好的。
Rome became a republic.
罗马成为共和国。
And Rome, the republic, will become the model
罗马，作为共和国，将成为模型
for the
的
British empire as well as the American republic.
英国帝国与美国共和国。
Okay? So, it's very important that you
好？所以，你很重要要理解罗马共和国的概念。
understand the Rome idea of republic.
了解罗马共和国的概念。
Okay? So, a republic is, again,
好的？所以，共和国又是，一由法律、传统统治的社会。
a society governed by
由法律、传统统治的社会。
laws, tradition,
and history.
和历史。
Okay? And
好？然后
these three things are manifested in the nobility.
这三件事在贵族中得以体现。
Okay? What the Romans call patricians.
好？罗马人称之为贵族。
And the patricians will exercise power for something called the Senate.
贵族将以参议院为名行使。
Okay? And it's this very idea that
好？正是这点概念。
Rome is ultimately a culture,
罗马最终是一种文化，
a republic, governed by laws,
一个由法律、传统统治的共和国，
tradition, and
并且…
history is what will allow it to expand very quickly until it dominates the entire Mediterranean.
历史将使其迅速扩张，直至统领整个地中海。
These patricians are the ones who will
这些贵族是将要
establish these international networks
建立这些国际网络
that will make the Roman Republic
那将使罗马共和国变得连贯。好吗？他们会通过赞助者的概念来做到这一点。
coherent. Okay? And they will do so through the idea of a patron
那将使罗马共和国连贯。好吗？他们会通过赞助者的概念来做到这一点。
client relationship.
客户关系。
Okay? So the idea is you have a patriarch
好了？意思是你有一个宗主。
and then the patriarch has
然后，宗主拥有
clients. And this will expand
客户。并且这将扩展
across the entire
贯穿整个
Mediterranean. So in other words,
地中海。换句话说，
the emperor is just one among equals.
皇帝只是同等者之一。
The emperor has his empire but these patriarchs
皇帝拥有自己的帝国，但这些宗主……
have their own empires within the empire.
拥有各自的帝国在帝国之内。
Okay? And this gives Rome,
好的？这也让罗马……
even though it's very spread out, a
即使它很分散，却有一种连贯性和统一性，正是大多数帝国所缺乏的。
coherence and a unity between the empires that most empires don't have.
再者，这点对我们很重要，因为英国人会照此模式去做。
And again, this is important for us because the British will copy this model
when they build their empire.
当他们建造自己的帝国时。
Okay? As well as the Americans.
好吧？美国人也一样。
The problem with this system though is that
但这种制度的问题在于……
if the patriarchs don't like the emperor,
如果宗主们不喜欢皇帝，
the patriarchs can get together and
宗主们可以聚在一起，
depose the emperor which
推举皇帝并罢位
has happened a lot of times throughout the history of the Roman Republic.
在罗马共和国的历史中，这种情况已经发生过很多次。
So think of Julius Caesar, right?
想想朱利叶·凯撒吧，对吧？
Julius Caesar wanted more power for himself
朱利叶·凯撒想为自己争取更多权力。
and so the patriarchs got together and killed him.
于是宗主们聚在一起，杀了他。
But Julius Caesar was just one of many.
但朱利叶·凯撒只是其中之一。
There was also Caligula, Nero,
还有加利古拉、尼禄等人。
and these and a lot more emperors.
以及这些，还有许多皇帝。
Okay? So
好吧？于是
because of this new emperors but especially people like
因为这些新皇帝，尤其是像……的人
Diocletian are the most
多克利安是最…
people Diocletian was a military general who
多克利安是一名军阙…
won the Roman Civil War and so became emperor.
他赢得罗马内战…
They had to fix this problem.
他们必须解决这个问题。
Okay? Because obviously if you're emperor your biggest problem is how do you stay alive?
好吧？因为显而如果你是皇帝，最大的问题就是你怎么能活下来？
And in the Roman Republic
在罗马共和国中
the chances of you staying alive aren't very high.
你存活的机会不高。
Okay? So starting with Diocletian they started to develop an imperial bureaucracy
好吧？于是从多克利安开始，他们开始发展帝国官僚体系。
to counter the power of the
以此来对抗其权力。
nobility. Okay?
贵族。好吧？
The problem though
问题是这样的
is like the nobility solves three problems for you
贵族为你解决了三个问题
that the bureaucracy cannot solve.
那是官僚体系无法解决的。
Okay? The first is a problem of the will to fight.
好吧？第一是战斗意志的问题。
The second is unity.
第二是统一。
The third
第三个
is culture.
是文化。
Okay? So
好吧？所以
the will to fight means like in a war the nobility are those
战斗意志就是像在战争中，贵族是最有失去之物的，因此最愿意去死。
who have the most to lose and therefore
they're the most willing to die.
战斗意志就是像在战争中，贵族是最有失去之物的，因此最愿意去死。
So think about the year 216
于是想想216年
when Hannibal invaded the Italian peninsula
当汉尼拔入侵意大利半岛
and he had to destroy all the Roman armies.
他必须消灭所有罗马军队
At this point Rome should have surrendered
此时罗马本应投降
but nobility refused to surrender because
但贵族却不投降，因为
if they surrendered then
若他们投降……
Hannibal would have instituted changes to their culture
汉尼拔会对他们的文化作出改变
that would have destroyed the prestige power
这些改变会破坏贵族的声望与权力
and wealth of nobility.
并消耗他们的财富
That's why the nobility refused to surrender.
这就是贵族不投降的原因。
They fought to the very bitter end and eventually they were able to triumph over Carthage.
他们奋战至极，最终战胜迦特。
Okay? So the will to fight. The nobility gives a society the will to fight.
于是，贵族赋予社会战斗之意。
Second of course is unity.
第二点当然是统一。
Okay? National unity.
好的？国家统一。
The third is culture.
第三点是文化。
So the people who
于是，写下罗马史的人正是贵族。
wrote the history of Rome were actually the nobility.
他们是参议员。贵族。
They were the senators. The aristocrats.
Okay? So when
好的？那么当
you get rid of nobility you lose these three things.
你去掉贵族后，你会失去这三件事。
You lose the idea of a national unity a national identity.
你失去国家统一的概念，国家身份。
You lose culture. You lose the will to fight.
你失去文化。你失去战斗的意志。
Okay? And that's why for the longest time the system stayed in place.
好吧？这也是为什么系统能持续最长时间的原因。
Because to
因为……
reject the nobility to kill all the nobility would be to destroy the tradition,
放弃贵族，消灭贵族就是要消灭罗马的传统、文化和历史。
culture, and history of Rome.
好的？但…
Alright? But
Diocletian would try to solve this problem by implementing imperial bureaucracy.
多里克里安将尝试通过实施帝国官僚来解决这个问题。
But the imperial bureaucracy could not challenge the authority,
但帝国官僚无法挑战贵族的权力与合法性。
power, and legitimacy of nobility.
Okay? That's why Constantine
好的？这就是康斯坦丁在330年的决定。
would in 330
move the capital to Byzantium
把首都迁至拜占庭
and create the Byzantine Empire.
并创建拜占庭帝国
Okay? And as we discussed previously the Byzantine Empire folk had imperial bureaucracy
好的？正如我们之前讨论的，拜占庭帝国的百姓拥有帝国官僚。
and it was the dominant power
并且它是主导力量。
and so
并且
the Byzantine Empire is not a continuation of the Roman
拜占庭帝国并非罗马的延续
Empire it is a rejection of the Roman Republic.
帝国即是对罗马共和国的否定。
Okay? So does that make sense?
好？这样说有道理吗？
The history of Rome.
罗马的历史。
Okay. This is important for us because the same thing will happen in China.
好的。这对我们很重要，因为同样的事会在中国发生。
Okay? The same thing will happen in China.
好的。类似的事会在中国发生。
After the Tang Dynasty the Song Dynasty will look at the mistakes of the Tang Dynasty
唐朝之后，宋朝会回顾唐朝的失误。
and they will start to implement a um
于是他们开始实施……
implement the Kejiu system and
实施科举制度并
create an imperial bureaucracy that will
创建一个皇室官僚体系，随后统治中国千年。
rule China for the next thousand years.
rule China for thenext thousand years.
Okay? Alright.
好的？好吧。
So the Kejiu.
于是科举。
There is a
有一个
great great misconception in China
在中国的巨大误解
that the Kejiu is a
那是科举是一个功名制。
meritocracy. But it is not a meritocracy.
但它并不是功名制。
It was never designed to be a meritocracy.
它从来不是为了功名制而设立的。
I know that in school you are taught that
我知道在学校里你们会被教到
they have the Kejiu in order for the Emperor to select the best
他们把科举安排成让皇帝挑选中国最优秀的
and brightest in China and because of the best
并且最聪明的
and brightest they will rule China virtuously.
并且最聪明的，他们将以德治国。
That's what you've been taught in school. That is not correct.
这就是你们在学校里学到的。那不对。
That's not what the Kejiu is designed for.
那不是科举的初衷。
The Kejiu is designed
科举的初衷是
for the Emperor to localize the elites and to divide and conquer them.
让皇帝把精英本土化并分而合之。
So let me explain why it's not a meritocracy.
于是我来说明它为什么不是单纯的功绩制。
First thing. First thing about the Kejiu that's important for us is
第一件事。关于科举对我们重要的第一件事是……
that there's a quota system in place.
还有一个配额制度在运作。
Okay? So
好的？那么
if it was just a meritocracy then the very best and brightest would win out.
如果只是功绩制，最优秀的才会脱颖而出。
Right? But think about the Gaokao.
对吧？再想想高考。
Okay? If it was just a meritocracy
好的？如果只是功绩制
then who would get into like top universities in China?
那么谁能进入中国顶尖的大学？
I assure you that 90% of all the top students would come from two cities.
我保证，90%的顶尖学生来自这两座城市。
Right? Beijing and Shanghai. Right?
对吧？北京和上海。对吧？
But that's not how the system works.
但那不是系统的运作方式。
There is a quota system in place.
有配额制度在运作。
There's geographic distribution. Only certain number of students from Beijing
有地域分布。只有一定数量的学生来自北京。
and Shanghai can get into Beijing and Tsinghua.
上海也能进入北京和清华。
The rest come from the provinces.
其余来自各省。
Okay? And the Kejiu is the same system.
好的？而科举也是同样的制度。
So let's look at it very quickly.
那我们快速看一下。
You're at the center. Everyone's trying to get into the center.
你在中心。大家都在争着进中心。
Let's say you have province A, B, C, and D.
假设你有省A、B、C、D。
And they're all the same. You have 10 wealthy families.
他们都一样。你有10个富裕家族。
Okay? And you have 10,000
好的？你有10,000。
poor families. Okay? Peasants.
贫家。好的吗？农民。
How this system works is
这个制度是怎么运作的。
A will send two,
A会派两支队伍，
D will send two, B will send two, C will send two.
D会派两支队伍，B会派两支队伍，C会派两支队伍。
Okay? And when
好的？然后
you do it this way this creates competition among the local elites.
你这样做会让地方精英之间产生竞争。
Right? To win these positions.
对吧？为了赢得这些位置。
And therefore they will fight amongst themselves.
于是他们会互相争斗。
Does that make sense? If you don't do it this way if it's just the best
这样说对吗？如果不这么做，只是最好的话。
and brightest then what will happen is like A, B,
并且最亮的那个人，接下来会发生的事就像A、B、…
C, D will compete amongst themselves and
C、D会在彼此之间竞争，且
eventually one of the provinces like maybe B will develop the innovation
最终可能会有一个省份像B那样发展出创新
in order for their children to always finish first or place the top in the province.
为了让他们的孩子总是第一名或在省里排第一。
Okay? Does that make sense guys? Alright?
好吧？这样说对吗？好吗？
So it's not meritocracy it's a quota system.
所以不是按才干计的，而是配额制。
That's the first thing.
那是第一件事。
Second thing you need to understand is that it is unfair.
第二件事是你需要理解的，它是不公平的。
Why is it unfair? Well because
为什么不公平？因为……
in order to do well on the keju remember
为了在科举中考得好，记住科举是考你对一种叫文言的东西的知识。
the keju is testing your knowledge of something called
文言是古文的意思。
wen yan. Okay?
好了？
Or classical Chinese.
或古典中文。
Classical literary
古典文学
Chinese. Okay?
中文。好吗？
This is a very hard skill to learn.
这是一个非常难学的技能。
It will take you decades. You will need private tutoring.
需要你花上几十年。你还要请私人辅导。
Your family needs to have a lot of money.
你的家族需要有很多钱。
You need to spend decades on this project which means that you have a lot of leisure time.
你需要花上几十年来完成这个项目，这意味着你有很多闲暇时间。
You don't have to work. Okay? So in other words
你不必工作。好吗？换句话说，只有……
only the elite families of China can compete in the system
只有中国的精英家族才能在这个体系中竞争。
and that's the point. Okay?
并且就是这个点。好吗？
The point is to concentrate on the ambition
点是把精英家族的雄心聚焦在科举上。
and energy of the elite families into the keju.
精英家族的精力投入科举。
Otherwise they might come up with ideas like rebellion.
否则他们可能会想到叛乱之类的主意。
Okay? They also might come up with
好吧？他们也可能想到新的发明和精彩的文学。
new inventions and amazing literature
but they'll also probably think of ways to rebel.
但他们也可能想到叛乱之路。
Okay? That's why you want to concentrate their energies on the keju.
好吧？这就是你要把他们的精力聚焦在科举上的原因。
Right? Does that make sense?
对吗？这样说通吗？
The third thing that's really important for us to remember is that
第三件事我们要记住的就是这点
this system is
这个制度是自选的
discretionary. What does that mean?
这是什么意思？
It means that just because
这意味着，光是你在科举中第一名，并不代表你成为官员。
you finish first on the keju does not mean you become a government official.
好吧？你们明白了吗？
Okay? Do you guys understand?
Success on the keju does not translate into success in politics.
科举成功并不等同政治成功。
It is discretionary meaning the emperor gets to decide
它是自选的，意思是皇帝决定谁成为官员，谁晋升。
who becomes an official and who gets promoted.
谁成为官员，谁晋升。
Only the emperor. Alright?
只有皇帝。好吧？
And often what will happen is the emperor will
而且往往
start to promote the government and he may be someone from the poor families.
开始推广政府，他可能是来自贫困家庭的人。
Okay? So not poor but lower nobility.
好的？所以不是贫贱，而是下层贵族。
And the reason why you want to do that
而你想这么做的原因是……
is to create a precarious situation in the provinces
在省份中制造不安的局面
where no family feels secure enough to feel as
让各家族都不安稳
though they're the nobility. Okay?
虽然是贵族。好吗？
You want to create conflict and precariousness in the provinces divide and conquer.
你想在省份制造冲突与不安，分而治之。
And therefore you can exert greater control
于是你就能更好地掌控各省。
over the provinces.
But by doing that you limit economic economic growth.
但这样做会限制经济增长。
You limit cultural innovation.
你限制了文化创新。
Does that make sense guys?
那有道理吗，大家？
Alright, so
好的，接下来是……
what this means is the
这意味着的就是
bureaucracy is able to control China
官僚能够掌控中国
because of its monopoly.
因为它的垄断
It has a monopoly over three aspects.
它在三个方面拥有垄断。
Alright, the first is status.
好，第一点是地位。
Alright, so if you want to be admired,
好，若你想被赞赏，
if you want to be respected in China, you do well in a kouju and you become an official.
如果你想在中国得到尊重，就要考好科举，成为官员。
That's a dream of every family in China right.
这正是中国每个家庭的梦想，对吧。
It's still true today right where
今天仍然如此，对吧。
the dream of every Chinese family is for you guys to get into an Ivy League school
中国每个家庭的梦想是你们能考上常春藤学校
and or take the gaokao and
或者考上高考
go to Peking or Tsinghua.
然后去北京或清华
Okay. Okay. The idea of status is still associated with the keju,
好的。好的。身份的概念仍与科举挂钩，
even though we know
即便我们知道
that success on the keju and
科举成功与…
success on the gaokao does not necessarily translate into success in school or in life.
高考成功不一定能转化为学校或生活上的成功。
That's the first thing. The second is the monopoly over literacy.
这就是第一点。第二点是文字的垄断。
The monopoly over literacy.
文字的垄断。
What I mean by that is this.
我说的意思是这样。
In most cultures,
在大多数文化里，
your goal is to make literacy more widespread.
你的目标是让文字更普及。
Because when you do that, you allow for faster economic development.
因为这样做，你就能更快地推动经济发展。
So throughout history,
于是，历史长河里，
all cultures have tried to figure
各个文化都曾试图弄清楚。
out how to make literacy more widespread.
我说的意思是这样。
Okay? So let's look at an example of Egypt.
好的？那我们来看看埃及的例子。
Egypt has been around for as long as China.
埃及的历史与中国一样悠久。
And over centuries,
于是，历经数百年，
they would make their language a lot easier to understand.
他们把自己的语言变得更易懂。
So in the beginning, they had hieroglyphics.
于是，起初时他们使用的是象形文字。
So maybe the sun. This represents sun.
也许是太阳。它代表太阳。
This is moon. Okay?
这就是月亮。好吗？
So that's the first stage. They have pictograms to represent the sun.
这就是第一阶段。他们用象形文字来表示太阳。
And then
于是
they would make the symbols shorter.
他们把符号写得更短
So it's easier to remember. And then
这样更容易记住
what they would do is they would make these symbols phonological.
他们会把这些符号变成音素。
Meaning they don't represent ideas.
意思是它们不代表概念。
They represent sounds. Okay?
它们代表声音。好吗？
So this now becomes the English word monsoon.
于是它变成了英文单词monsoon。
Right? Does that make sense?
对吗？这样说通吗？
And then what they would do is they would make the symbols phonological.
然后他们会把符号变成音素。
And then what they would do is they would take the word
然后他们会把这个词取出来
and
并且
make it into just one consonant.
变成仅一个辅音。
Okay? So this would become S.
好的？于是它会变成S。
This would become M.
它会变成M。
And therefore, you now have the English word sum.
于是你现在得到英文单词sum。
Okay? And that's why we have the alphabet.
好的？这就是我们有字母表的原因。
Because of this evolution of language in Egypt.
因为这就是埃及语言的演变。
It was the Egyptians who developed this system.
正是埃及人发展了这一体系。
And then the Greeks stole it.
然后希腊人把它偷走了。
Through the Phoenicians.
通过腊人。
Okay? Alright?
好的吗？
So most cultures follow this pattern.
所以大多数文化都遵循这一模式。
Because now it's easier for people to become literate.
因为现在人们更容易成为文盲。
Which just drives economic growth. Okay?
这又推动了经济增长。
China is the only culture in human history
中国是人类历史上唯一使文字更难以掌握的文化
that has made literacy more difficult over time.
好的吗？中国把……
Alright? China took the...
Pythograms. Pythograms. And made them even more complex.
毕图格拉姆。毕图格拉姆。并使其更为复杂。
And added these very complex grammatical rules to the language.
并加入了这些极为复杂的语法规则。
And created something called literary Chinese.
并创造了所谓的文言文。
Okay? Literary Chinese. But that's a nice...
好的？文言文。但那是个不错的……
That's a euphemism. That's a nice way of saying it.
那是个委婉说法。那是一种不错的表达方式。
It really... What it is is bureaucratat.
它真的……就是官僚化。
Bureaucraties. Okay?
官僚化。好吧？
Bureaucraties is a language that only bureaucrats can understand.
官僚化是一种只有官僚才能理解的语言。
So think of contracts.
想想合同吧。
Right? When you look at legal contracts.
对吧？看法律合同的时候。
You can't read it. Why?
你看不懂。为什么？
Because the language, the grammar is designed
因为语言、语法是专门设计的。
so that only as a specialized lawyer could you understand the contract.
于是只有专业律师才能理解合同。
Right? And this is what we call rent seeking behavior.
对吧？这就是我们所说的租金寻求行为。
You create something that only you can use and
你创造了只有你能使用的东西。
people have to pay rent in order to access your knowledge.
人们必须付租金才能获得你的知识。
Alright? So literacy,
好吧？所以识字率，
the problem with literacy will keep China back from developing.
识字率的问题会让中国落后发展。
And the third is culture.
第三点是文化。
Okay? Culture.
好的？文化。
And when I mean culture I really mean Confucianism. So
当我说文化时，我指的就是儒学。
Confucianism is really a bureaucratic philosophy
儒学是一种行政哲学体系
system designed to maintain the status quo.
旨在维持现状
To control how people think about the world.
控制人们对世界的思考
Alright? So remember in the Confucian religion.
好的？记住在儒学里。
What really matters first and
首先最重要的是平衡，和谐。
foremost is balance, harmony.
There's also a concept called ancestor worship.
还有一个叫做祖先祭祀的概念。
So you can't leave your village.
于是你就不能离开你的村庄。
Because if you leave your village you can no longer worship your ancestors.
因为一旦离开村庄，你就再也不能祭祀你的祖先。
Right? You can't clean their graves.
对吧？你们不能去扫墓。
And so people are just stuck in place.
于是人们就只会停留在原地。
And that limits trade and innovation in China.
这限制了中国的贸易和创新。
Okay? So the Kuju.
好的？那就说说古句。
Sorry. The bureaucracy,
抱歉。官僚，
the imperial bureaucracy was able to maintain its monopoly over status,
皇室官僚能维持其地位独占。
literacy, and culture through three mechanisms.
识字与文化通过三种机制实现。
The Kuju, Wenyan,
古句、文言、文学汉语，和儒学。
literary Chinese, and Confucianism.
Okay? And that stopped the development of,
好吧？而这又停止了...
that
那
stopped the cultural
停止了文化
and economic development of China.
和中国的经济发展。
Okay? So let's better understand this idea.
好的？那我们更好理解这个想法。
Okay. In a society there are different ways to seek success
好的。在社会中有不同的方式来追求成功
and status.
和地位。
Alright? So you have the bureaucracy of course.
好的？所以你有了官僚体系。
And that's the way people do it in China.
这就是中国人做事的方式。
But you also have the military.
但你也有军队。
You also have nobility.
你也有贵族。
Right? Chinese nobility.
对吧？中国贵族。
You also have church.
你也有教会。
Religion. Right?
宗教。对吧？
By becoming a priest.
通过成为神职。
By becoming a spiritual leader.
通过成为灵性领袖。
You also have merchants.
你也有商人。
Right? Commerce.
对吧？商业。
You can also do it through artistic endeavors.
你也可以通过艺术创作来实现。
Okay? So these are the main ways people achieve status in society.
好吧？所以这些是人们在社会中获得地位的主要方式。
And in most societies you have these different systems in place.
而在大多数社会中，你会有这些不同的制度在运作。
What is unique about China is the dominance of the bureaucracy.
中国的独特之处在于官僚的主导地位。
Okay? So the nobility was wiped out.
好吧？于是贵族被消除。
And through the Kezhu, the Kezhu ensures that
而通过科举，科举确保了……
no nobility can arise again in China.
没有贵族能在中国再次出现。
Okay? Church religion was outlawed for most of Chinese history.
好吧？教会宗教在中国历史大部分被废除。
Okay? The merchant
好吧？商人
and the artistic people are low status in China.
艺术人士在中国的社会地位低。
So go back to the Confucian system.
于是回到儒学制度。
The scholar officials are at the top.
学士官员位居顶层。
Then you have the farmers.
然后是农民。
Then you have the merchants. And you have the artists.
然后是商人。还有艺术家。
Right? So the Confucian religion puts the merchants
对吧？于是儒学把商人放在……
and the artists at the very bottom.
艺术家位于最底层。
And this is intentional because the artists, okay,
这点是有意安排的，因为艺术家，嗯，……
they can promote new ideas.
他们能推广新思想。
But the merchants are even more problematic because they trade.
但商人更麻烦，因为他们做买卖。
Okay? And they can accumulate wealth.
好吧？他们还能聚财。
And that wealth can challenge the authority of the empire.
这笔财可以挑战帝国的权威。
Alright? So the merchants are a problem.
好的？商人是个问题。
The military, as we know,
正如我们所知，军队，
was heavily suppressed throughout Chinese history.
在中国历史上被大力压制。
So the Song Dynasty,
于是宋朝出现了
there was these massive conflicts between the military and the bureaucracy.
军队与官僚之间的巨大冲突
The military wanted to go fight and defend Song territory.
军队想出征战、保卫宋土
The bureaucracy wanted to just bribe everyone.
官僚只想给大家行贿。
Okay? Alright?
好？好吧？
Okay. So, and because you have too much power, you have to have a lot of money.
好了。于是，手握大权，手握大财。
You have to have power over the bureaucracy. This was stunt development in China.
你必须掌握官僚的权力。这是中国的突发发展。
Alright. Let's look at one more example.
好吧。再看一个例子。
Okay? We know that by the time of the Song,
我们知道，到宋朝时……
China had four major inventions.
中国拥有四大发明。
Okay? These four major inventions, of course, are paper,
好？这四大发明，当然是纸张，
printmaking,
印刷，
compass,
罗盘，
and gunpowder.
火药。
Alright? And these four inventions, guys,
好的？这四大发明，大家，
will revolutionize the world.
将革新世界。
Alright? So if you look at paper, it will give rise to banknotes.
好吧？看纸张，它会催生纸币。
Okay? So the stone had banknotes. And
好？于是石头也有纸币。
this will give rise to capitalism in the West.
这将催生西方的资本主义。
Printmaking is important because remember, in the 15th century,
印刷业之所以重要，记得，十五世纪，古腾堡在欧洲发明了印刷机。
Gutenberg created something called the printing press in Europe.
And because of the printing press, you're now able to print.
因为印刷机的出现，你现在可以印刷。
You're able to manufacture books at scale.
你可以大规模制造书籍。
And when you do that, what happens is that people become more literate.
这样一来，人们的读写能力就会提升。
So the very idea of the printing press made available all these books,
于是印刷机的出现，使得这些书籍得以流通，
all this knowledge that wasn't available before.
这些知识以前未曾流通，
And now people could just learn how to read and write.
于是人们便能学会读写。
Okay? So this will give rise to literacy.
好的？这样就会促成读写能力的提升。
And when you give rise to literacy, you will give rise to things like the Renaissance,
当你促成读写能力的提升时，你也会促成文艺复兴、文艺复兴、文艺复兴等事物的出现。
the Protestant Reformation, the Second Revolution,
文艺复兴、文艺复兴、文艺复兴等事物的出现。
the Enlightenment, the French Revolution.
启蒙运动，法国大革命。
So this marked a revolution in European affairs.
这标志着欧洲事务的革命。
The compass, right, will allow for the age of exploration.
指南针，正是让探险时代得以开启。
So these Europeans are able to discover new lands
于是这些欧洲人能够发现新大陆
and conquer and colonize them.
并征服并殖民之
Right? So North America,
对吧？于是北美洲，
South America will eventually all become colonized by the Europeans using the compass.
南美洲最终将被使用指南针的欧洲人全部殖民。
Gunpower is important because it is the,
火炮力量重要，因为它是，
it is a revolution in warfare.
它是战争的革命。
From gunpower, you will have things like the war.
从火炮力量开始，你将拥有类似战争的事物。
You will have things like the cannon. And also eventually the musket.
你将拥有大炮之类的事物；随后又出现了火枪。
The musket is just an individual gun.
火枪仅是单兵武器。
And this marks a revolution not only in warfare
这标志着战争的革命
but also in human affairs.
也标志着人类事务的革命
Because when you have the musket,
因为当你拥有火枪时
now individual soldiers do matter.
现在单兵也开始重要。
Okay? Before, it was a knight who
好？之前是骑士才是战场的主力。
was the main weapon in the warfare.
骑士是战争中的主要武器。
But now we have a musket,
但现在我们拥有火枪，
you can now equal the playing field.
你现在可以把战场拉平了。
Okay? It's more important to have more soldiers than to have knights.
好？拥有更多士兵比骑士更重要。
And this will allow for things like the American Revolution.
这将使得美国革命等事件成为可能。
Right? When you have these farmers with muskets,
对吧？当你拥有这些农民手持火枪时，
they were able to overthrow the British Empire.
他们就能推翻英国帝国。
It will give rise to the French Revolution when
它将促成法国大革命，当时有了非职业士兵的市民。
you have citizens who are not professional soldiers.
他们将拿起火枪，保卫本国抵御欧洲入侵。
They will take these muskets and defend their country against a European invasion.
All right? So all these are major revolutions
一切都对吗？所以这些都是重要的革命
that will give rise to modernity.
它们将促成现代化的出现
Okay? And again, China, by the Song Dynasty,
好的？再说一次，宋代的中国
1200 CE,
1200年，
had all four inventions.
拥有四大发明。
But because of the culture in place, because of the bureaucratic culture in place,
但由于当时的文化，尤其是官僚文化。
neither, not any of these inventions had an impact in Europe.
没有一项发明在欧洲产生影响。
And China did nothing whatsoever with all four inventions.
中国对四大发明也没有任何运用。
All right? So, the key lesson here,
好了，关键的结论是：】
guys, and this is really important, technology does not matter.
伙计们，这点很重要，技术本身不算数。
You can steal the technology.
你可以偷技术。
What matters is the culture.
关键在于文化。
All right? Another example,
好了？再举个例子，
of course, is the UN Dynasty.
当然是UN王朝。
When the UN Dynasty,
在UN王朝时期，
during the UN Dynasty, China was importing a lot of foreign experts,
在UN王朝期间，中国大量引进外籍专家，大量外籍官员。基督徒、穆斯林、犹太人。
a lot of foreign bureaucrats. Christians, Muslims,
他们大量引进外籍技术。
Jews. They were importing a lot of foreign technology.
Jews. They were importing alot of foreign technology.
And then, when the Ming Empire came into place,
然后，明朝建立后，他们把这些东西都摆了出去。
they got rid of all this stuff.
他们把外来的人都摆了出去。
Okay? They got rid of the foreigners. They got rid of the technology.
他们把技术也都摆了出去。
China became much more insular and backward. Okay?
中国变得更内向、更落后。好吗？
Okay. So, that explains why China is so important.
好的。所以，这就解释了中国为何如此重要。
After the Song Dynasty, China did not innovate anymore,
宋朝之后，中国再也没有创新。
because the empire did not want to innovate.
因为帝国不想创新。
Innovation is a threat to the status quo.
创新是对现状的威胁。
Okay? And
好吧？然后。
what's important is to maintain the status quo.
重要的是保持现状。
Even though, by doing so,
即便如此，做了之后，
ultimately you make China poor,
最终你会让中国变穷。
weak, and divided.
弱而分散。
All right. Good.
好的。不错。
Any questions? Does it make sense to you guys?
有问题吗？你们觉得有道理吗？
Does this conform to your understanding of Chinese history?
这符合你对中国历史的理解吗？
Yeah. Okay.
是的，好的。
So, the question is, is Confucianism a religion or a culture?
那么问题是，儒家是宗教还是文化？
So, no one thinks Confucianism is a religion.
于是，没人认为儒家是宗教。
At most, people will say that Confucianism is a civic or a religious religion.
最多人会说儒家是公民宗教或宗教。
Okay? Or a philosophy.
好吧？或者是哲学。
All right? So,
好的？那么，
I would say that Confucianism,
我想说的是儒家，
ultimately, what it is,
最终，它是什么，
is bureaucratism.
是官僚主义。
I can't even spell bureaucrat anymore.
我连官僚都拼不出来。
Okay? Bureaucratism. Okay? What I mean by that is that
好了？官僚主义。好了？我说的就是这个。
it is something that's designed to,
它是一种被设计成的东西，
you know, to be a kind of a society that
你知道，像一种社会，
makes everyone believe that a bureaucratic society is the best society.
让大家都相信官僚社会是最好的社会。
It is one that is the most sophisticated.
它是最精细的那一种。
And it's designed in order to maintain a status quo
它的设计是为了维持现状，官僚位居顶端。
where bureaucrats are at the top. Okay?
好了？
That's what Confucianism really is.
这才是儒家真正的面貌。
So, the example is that if you read Chinese history,
举个例子：如果你读中国历史，
the most virtuous people are always bureaucrats, scholar officials.
最有德行的人总是官僚、书生。
All right? And this propaganda is so effective that eventually Europeans will be like, oh, we're going to have to stop.
好了？这场宣传如此有效，最终欧洲人会说：哦，我们得停了。
We'll stop. We'll start to mimic this propaganda.
我们会停下来，开始模仿这种宣传。
So Voltaire, the French Enlightenment thinker,
于是伏尔泰，法国启蒙思想家。
says that Chinese have the best system because
说中国有最好的制度，因为只有受过教育的人才能执政。
they allow only the educated to rule.
不是士兵，也不是祭司，而是……
Not soldiers, not priests, but
scholar officials.
学者官员。
Mandarins. Okay?
令士。好吗？
So, this is, so the idea of Confucianism is that it's bureaucratism.
所以，这就是，故此，儒学的意思是官僚主义。
It's designed to legitimize and
它的设计是为了使其合法化并且
give authority to the bureaucratic community.
赋予官僚社区权威。
And it's not like elite. All right?
并且它并非精英化。
So, so, so thank you.
所以，太感谢了。
Does that make sense to you? Okay. Any more questions?
这对你来说有道理吗？好了，还有别的问题吗？
Okay. So, I'm going to end the class with a story.
好了，我要用一个故事来结束这节课。
Okay? And the story has to do with the first emperor of the Ming Dynasty,
好的？故事要跟明朝第一位皇帝朱元璋有关。
Zhu Yuanzhang. So, Zhu Yuanzhang, he is now emperor.
所以，朱元璋，他现在是皇帝。
Okay? And he reinstitutes the Kezhu.
好的？他恢复了科举。
Okay? The Mongols got rid of the Kezhu
好的？蒙古人把科举废掉了。
because they had a nobility.
因为他们有贵族。
But Zhu Yuanzhang, he restores the Kezhu.
但朱元璋，他恢复了科举。
And everyone's excited. Okay? So, everyone comes and takes the examination.
大家都很兴奋。好吧？于是大家都来参加考试。
When the results come out, what happens is
当成绩公布时，发生了……
that the test takers from the south do a lot better than the north.
南方考生的成绩明显优于北方。
So these northern test takers feel there must be corruption in place.
于是北方考生们认为一定有腐败。
So, they file a petition to the emperor.
于是他们向皇帝递交请愿。
The emperor looks at the petition and he agrees there must be corruption.
皇帝审阅请愿后，认为必有贪污。
How is it that no northerner was able to pass the Kezhu?
...
So, he calls in his chief minister and he says, this is a huge scandal.
于是，他召见首相，告知这是一场大闹剧。
I want you to resolve this issue.
我想让你解决这个问题。
Okay? Figure out who's responsible for this corruption and kill them.
好吗？查清谁是这腐败的责任人，然后把他们杀了。
All right? So, the chief minister,
好的？于是，首相，
he really wants to impress the emperor.
他真想给皇帝留下深刻印象。
So, he spends months painstakingly,
于是，他花了数月精心地
rigorously examining the issue, investigating the issue.
严谨地审查问题，调查问题。
He has commission. He has hundreds of staff.
他有委托。手下有数百名员工。
He personally looks at every single Kezhu.
他亲自查看每一个客主。
And then he writes his report.
随后他写下报告。
He presents it to the emperor.
他把它呈给皇帝。
Okay? And he says to the emperor,
好的？然后他对皇帝说，
your majesty,
阁下
I personally have done this investigation.
我亲自完成了这项调查。
And we have written like thousands of pages of reports.
我们已经写了数千页的报告。
And I have written a report directly to you. And
我已直接向您写了一份报告。并且
I can guarantee you the Kezhu,
我可以向您保证凯朱
when implemented, was a fair, open,
实施时是公平、开放的
and transparent process.
且透明的过程。
The fact of the matter is that people in the south,
事实是南方的人更有文化。
they're more civilized.
他们更有文明。
They're more cultured.
他们更有文化。
They're more educated. And therefore,
他们更有教育。于是，
they just did better on the,
他们在……方面做得更好。
did better than the northerners.
他们做得比北方人更好。
And I'm really sorry this happened.
我很抱歉这件事发生了。
But I guarantee you the Kezhu is a fair, open, and transparent process.
但我保证，柯朱是一个公平、公开、透明的过程。
You have nothing to worry about. It's all been taken care of.
你没事儿，全部都已处理完毕。
So, what do you think the emperor did?
那么，你认为皇帝做了什么？
What do you think the emperor did? Have you guys heard of this story?
你们听说过这件事吗？
He killed them all. He killed the high official.
他把他们全都杀了。他杀了高官。
He killed the high official's commissioners.
他杀了高官的委派。
He killed the test makers.
他杀了试题人。
He killed those who got the very best scores on the Kezhu.
他杀了在科朱中获得最高分的那几个人。
The reason why is the emperor does not want a fair,
之所以如此，是因为皇帝想要一个公平、公开、透明的系统。
open, and transparent system.
He wants a system in which
他想要一个系统，其中地方不再起义。
the localities will not rebel against the center.
而这正是科朱的意义。
And that's what the Kezhu is.
于是，科朱就是这样一个系统。
All right. So, that is it.
好的，就是这样。
We will do Genghis Khan next class.
下节课我们来讲成吉斯·汗。